Guide to the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection, 1695-1955 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- H-K
  - Jackson, Andrew papers, 1820-1836
    Papers chiefly concern military and Indian affairs, including a fight with the British at Mobile, Ala., 1814; raids of the Creek and Seminole Indians; relations between the U. S. government and the Indians in Alabama; the use of U. S. troops to remove intruders from Cherokee lands; affairs of the military department of the South when Jackson was in command, 1816; construction of a military road from Nashville to New Orleans, 1816; and the Seminole War, 1835-1842. Several letters discuss politics during and after Jackson's presidency, including his relationships with John Rhea and John C. Calhoun. There is also material about military actions in Florida and Georgia during the War of 1812 and on government relations with the Creek Indians.
  - Jesup, Thomas Sidney papers, 1787-1860
    This collection consists military and other papers of Gen. Thomas Sidney Jesup relating mainly to the War of 1812, The Seminole War, and the Mexican War. It contains correspondence between Jesup and Major Willson, Hugh McCall, William Linnard, James Brown, L. P. Heintzelman, William Schley, and William Ballard Preston, among others. Topics are mostly related to military matters and relations with the Creeks and Seminoles. A detailed memoir by Jesup entitled "Memoir of the Campaigne on the Niagara" complements a similar item in the Jacob Jennings Brown Papers. Combined, the two memoirs yield a stunning overview of the Niagara Campaign, and also point to interesting areas of disagreement. Also included in the collection are two items from Washington, D.C., dated 1831. One represents the sale of 21 slaves to Jesup, while the other is the official District of Columbia authorization for such a sale, which is on Department of State Letterhead, and is signed by Secretary of State Edward Livingston. Additionally, the collection contains an 1813 article of agreement between Jesup and Brintnel Robins of Penn., who contracted to supply 65 boats for the U.S. troops. The boats were intended for the expedition that later led to the Battle of the Chippewa.
  - Johnson, Andrew papers, 1865
    This folder contains a draft of a petition to Johnson, 1865, requesting favorable action on the application for pardon submitted by James H. Wilson of Charlotte.
  - Johnson, Thomas papers, 1776-1779
    The collection consists of 24 items addressed to the Maryland Council of Safety (of which Johnson was a member) and to Thomas Johnson in his capacity as Governor of Maryland (1777-1779). Most of the letters and documents concern Revolutionary War matters, such as the raising of the militia, the difficulties in getting men to accept military commissions, loyalty vouchers for ships leaving Annapolis, and financial aspects such as checks for the payment of debts for supplies. Many names prominent in Maryland history are mentioned.
  - Jones, Iredell papers, 1842-1906
    Collection contains Jones's correspondence and focuses on the Civil War. Some letters are from Jones to his parents, written while a student at S.C. College and a member of a volunteer group concerned with abolition. In all of the letters he wrote with a terse style, relating news and events. He includes detailed accounts of the military activities surrounding Charleston and Fort Sumter, such as iron-clad battles, bombardment of Sumter and hand to hand combat. Letters of family members, including his brother Cadwallader (Waddy) Jones, also give vivid pictures of the military and social aspects of the war in a broad area of the South. There is an account of the June 1862 twelve-day forced march to Fredericksburg. Other correspondence reflects Jones's courtship and marriage to Ellen Adams. He may have been a member of the Ku Klux Klan and letters tell of his arrest and imprisonment in 1871. Other items include legal papers, miscellany such as an unidentified photograph, and papers concerning the United Confederate Veterans, including data on many veterans.
  - Kee, C. T. papers, 1866-1878
    Collection consists of one volume, which appears to be a records of compensation for agricultural labor. Most of the volume consists of lists of staples, foodstuffs, and cash given to laborers on a per diem basis from 1866 to 1878. The last few pages of the book contain written receipts from wages paid by C. T. Kee. All recipients have signed with an "X." This, and a reference to several laborers as "Freedmen" indicate that Kee's laborers were African American. If so, then this volume, covering the 10 years after the Civil War, is valuable documentation of the ways in which African Americans were co-opted into semi-slavery in many parts of the South.
  - Kelly, Henry Kuhl papers, 1933
    Collection consists of three short notes from Dr. Harry Atwood Kelly to his son Henry Kuhl Kelly. Dr. Kelly, a devout Christian, writes of his travels and cautions his son on the importance of a pious life and the temptations of alcohol.
  - Kendall, Amos papers, 1840-1849
    Letter (1840 May 20) from James W. Jeffreys, postmaster at Red House, Caswell County, N.C., to Kendall. The author congratulated Kendall on becoming editor of the Extra Globe and listed his qualifications for the position. Letter (1844 Oct. 7) from Andrew Jackson to Kendall. In his letter, Jackson told Kendall how he planned to try to overawe the "nulifiers" of S.C. with a force of around 150,000 volunteers from a number of states. If this did not work, he planned to punish the leaders only and not "their humble followers." Jackson reminisced about fighting the Creek Red Sticks in the Battle of Talladega and referred to the mutiny and disorder in his camp at Ten Islands. He also revealed that in his 1829 inaugural address, his friends persuaded him to strike a paragraph opposing the Bank of the United States as being unconstitutional. In closing, Jackson spoke of his shortness of breath when he attempted to walk unassisted. Letter from Sears Cook Walker (1849 Aug. 11) soliciting aid in connecting Southern Telegraph Company lines with the Charleston Observatory.
  - Kentucky, Miscellany papers, 1795-1865
    Collection of miscellaneous items from Kentucky, including a 1795 Commonwealth of Ky. land grant of 9,728 acres in Nelson Co. to Joseph Lewis, among other deed transferrals. Additional items include a letter of recommendation from George Bibb; a letter dated 3 August 1816, from R. Whiting in New York to James Prentiss in Lexington, Ky., concerning the failure of acceptance of bank drafts on the Mechanics Bank and other banks in Philadelphia and New York; and various business letters.
  - Kincaid, M. Virginia papers, 1875-1888
    This collection contains correspondence written to Virginia "Jennie" Kincaid of Collettsville, NC. The folder is located in Box 4 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - Knox family papers, 1837-1884
    The first item in this collection is a letter from Rome written in 1837 to John Knox of Leesville, S.C. The signature is missing from this item, which relates to the sights and art of Rome. The second item is a letter (1866) addressed to James Knox from Robert H. Miller of Lawrence, Kan. Miller discusses in detail his feelings about the recent Civil War. Most of the letter is devoted to a detailed and stirring account of Quantrill’s 1863 raid on Lawrence, Kan., and the extraordinary events that happened at Miller’s own house. The next three items pertain to W. D. Knox, the son [?] of James Knox. One item is a personal letter of family news written in 1872. Also from that year is a Davidson report card for W. D. Knox’s son, John. The final item (1884) is W. D. Knox’s appointment certificate as school commissioner for Chester County, S.C.
- L
  - Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert du Motier, Marquis de papers, 1825-1830
    Letter of Lafayette, 1825, written on board the "Natchez" on the Mississippi River, introducing Prince Achille Murat, son of the King of Naples, and a group of Murat's Neapolitan friends; letter from Lafayette in Halifax, N.C., responding to an invitation to visit Tarboro, N.C.; letter from Lafayette to unidentified friend, written from LaGrange, France, 1830, concerning funds for a statue of Thomas Jefferson to be commissioned in Europe on behalf of the University of Virginia (Lafayette favored the appointment of his friend Pierre-Jean David for this commission).
  - Langley family papers, 1855-1887
    This collection consists mainly of Civil War letters written by T. C. Langley (Company J, 12th Regiment, South Carolina Volunteers), to his family near Lancaster Courthouse, South Carolina. Many of the letters are addressed to his father, William C. Langley, and many South Carolina names are mentioned. Although T. C. Langley wrote regularly from 1861-1865, these letters have little military or political content and pertain mainly to personal matters. Langley's main concerns were his brother John (serving with him, and frequently ill) and the state of agricultural matters back home. The regiment to which Langley belonged traveled widely but little is revealed about camplife, battles, or war perspectives, other than occasional lists of casualties. Of interest at one point in the correspondence is the writer's anger that a Lancaster neighbor had tried to buy first T. C.'s father and then his little brother as substitutes in the army (1862). Miscellany for the collection is mainly pre-war legal material from Lancaster District, including small court suits and the settlement of a James Langley's estate. This folder is located in Box 5 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - Lane, Samuel papers, 1817
    One letter in which Lane informs Congress the new Representative and Senate Chambers will be ready by the autumn of 1818. Dated 1817, the letter includes reports from James Hoban, who was put in charge of rebuilding the White House after it was destroyed in the War of 1812. Hoban gives a detailed account of materials, costs and interior finishing and reveals that the Oval Office was originally called the "Elliptical Saloon."
  - Lee, Robert Edward papers, 1749-1975
    The Daltons gifted 27 items which help make up the Lee papers.
  - Lee, Thomas Sim papers, 1779-1782
    Correspondence directed to Governor Thomas Sim Lee of Maryland during the Revolutionary War. Included are two letters from Army provisioners, and various military letters concerning resignations and deserters. One letter from the General Council grants a man and wife the right to return to Great Britain despite the war; another, from Richard Barnes, solicits aid and describes British harassment of boats and citizens at the mouth of the Potomac.
  - Leech, Abraham Paul, 1796-1955(bulk 1840-1930)
    Correspondence, legal and financial papers, photographs, printed material, writings, clippings, and volumes relating chiefly to the Leech family, but also to relations in the Dewey, Warner, and Duryea families. Correspondence topics include: nineteenth-century American politics; reform movements; lectures and lyceums in New York; late nineteenth-century courtship; and school activities at the Stone School and Williams College. One series of letters from 1841 refer to the American poet Walt Whitman. Another series of letters from the Dewey family, beginning in the 1840s, originate from Ohio. Also included in this collection are papers concerning the Jamaica Lyceum, of which Abraham Paul Leech was secretary pro tem in the 1840s.
  - Legaré, Hugh Swinton papers, 1837-1843
    Miscellaneous correspondence concerning Legaré's legal practice, politics, and the purchase of books for his library. Letter to Legaré (1837) from jurist Frederick Grimke in Delaware, Ohio, while Legaré was in the U.S. Congress, relating to the organization of the court system in the Ohio area and Legaré's planned visit to the "western U. S." Also contains a letter, 1838, from Joel Poinsett, secretary of war of the United States, pertaining to a treaty with the Sioux Indians, and a letter from the sculptor, John Stevens Cogdell, concerning his career.
  - Leventhorpe, Collette papers, 1862-1931
    Records of Confederate Army's 11th Regiment of N.C., formerly 1st Infantry Regiment, also known as the "Bethel Regiment." Includes orders issued by Leventhorpe as commander of the regiment, and orders issued to Leventhorpe; final accounts of members who died in service and inventories of their personal effects; certificates of disability and discharge; and proceedings of courts-martial. Final accounts of deceased members include a physical description of individual, and often his former occupation. Also includes a 1931 clipping with a photograph of Leventhorpe.
  - Lincoln, Abraham papers, 1861-1938
    Chiefly facsimiles of Lincoln letters; clippings; and other miscellany concerning Lincoln and his assassination.
  - Lockyer, Edmund papers, 1811-1814
    Handbills and one letter related to British sale of goods captured from sailing ships during War of 1812. Handbills are for sales in Plymouth, England: one (1811) advertises the auction of the cargo of the brig "Fox," and includes detailed auction sheet; another advertises 1812 auction of the cargo of American schooner "Arrow", whose cargo included items such as silk, brandy, champagne, almonds, dress goods, and toys. Each handbill names William Lockyer as broker, and Edmund Lockyer as customs-house agent. A letter (1814) from George Tobin, captain of the H.M.S. "Andromache" asks Edmund Lockyer for payment of bounty on captured ship.
  - Long, Benjamin papers, 1854-1856
    The Daltons gifted 4 items in 1980 which were cataloged under James R. W. Sellwood's name. The items are correspondence from James Sellwood and his brother, John, to Benjamin Long of Mendon, Ill., chiefly concerning the Sellwoods' mission in and around Grahamville, Beaufort Co., S.C. The letters, including a copy of a report to the mission's trustees, describes Sellwood's living conditions and salary, the religious condition and lives of the inhabitants in and around Grahamville, sermon topics, and local customs. Sellwood also mentions the existing local prejudice against the Episcopal Church and that the Baptists attracted possible communicants away from Anglicanism.
  - Lucas Family papers, 1813-1867 and undated
    Correspondence, legal papers, and financial papers of the Lucas family of Raleigh, N.C. Early letters (1813-1816) were written by Alexander Lucas to his wife Mary while he visited Pennsylvania and Washington, D.C. Legal papers pertain to a lawsuit involving William Lucas, Henderson Lucas, and Margaret Lucas and concerning the estate and Revolutionary War military bounty of their grandfather, Thomas Lucas. A letter written to William Lucas from N. Davidson (1857) on an advertising sheet contains descriptions of inventions of 1857, including a counterfeit preventing machine for the printing of banknotes, a windmill, a pump, and a letter-copying press. Also included in the collection are letters (1861-1862) from Henderson Lucas of the 34th Regiment of N.C. Troops, Company G, to his sister Margaret. Lucas wrote from Camp Fisher near High Point, N.C., from Camp Davis near Wilmington, and from Hamilton's Crossing. Clippings include one describing Henderson Lucas' heroism at the battle of Gettysburg. Collection also includes a small account book (1821) in which Mary Lucas made a few brief entries.
- M-O
  - Maryland, Miscellany papers, 1775-1860
    Collection of miscellaneous items from Maryland. Includes correspondence and an indenture. This folder is located in Box 6 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - Mason, George papers, undated
    Collection consists of a photostat of pages six and seven of a letter from Mason to an unidentified relative. Mason tells him to proceed to execute a warrant and entry for a grant of land, and he will make an assignment of the entry to him. The land matter involves others, including Messrs. Steptoe and Gosnell. Mason writes that he has delivered to his son a hogshead of tobacco recently received from one of the addressee's tenants, and mentions a snuff mill with which his son Thomson was "concerned" for two years.
  - Mayer, Brantz papers, 1845-1890
    Papers including several letters concerning Bennet Allen, an 18th century Anglican clergymen, pertaining to a riot in Allen's parish and to property he left in America at the time of the Revolution; and correspondence and papers concerning Mayer's interest in Maryland history and archival sources and in the Maryland Historical Society.
  - McIntosh, Alexander papers, 1860-1865
    Chiefly letters to McIntosh from his wife and other relatives. Several are written to him in early 1865 while he was stationed with Company K, 4th Regiment, Senior Reserves in Salisbury, NC, and they primary concern his family and other personal news. Another letter, dated February 4, 1865, is to McIntosh's wife from her brother, R. Gerrard Sifford, while he was being held as a prisoner of war at Point Lookout, MD. McIntosh and his family lived in Martindale, Mecklenburg County, NC. This folder is located in Box 6 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - Medical College of Georgia records, 1833-1859
    Collection contains three items. The first is the bill (1833), creating the Medical College from the old Institute. It is signed by Governor Lumpkin and endows the college with funds, land, and trustees. The second item is an 1858 graduation statement, listing graduates and discussing briefly the fact that enrollment is down due to the local economy. A third letter (1859), is from F. Campbell at the college, informing an unknown addressee that he has been appointed to the Board of Trustees.
  - Megahey Family papers, 1861-1877
    Collection contains three letters from T.C. Megahey to his family in Charlotte, N.C. He recounts events of a trip to Petersburg, Va., and writes of camp life. For one letter, the stationery is from the U.S. Sanitary Commission. The final item is an April Fool's rhyme sent to Miss Mary Megahey.
  - Miscellany papers, 1695-1919
    These are miscellaneous items gifted by Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton. Included are deeds and correspondence, including a letter from Jonathan Trumbull, an 1865 oath of allegiance signed by James Stump, a ticket to the trial of Tilton vs. Beecher in 1874, and a rough draft of a letter [1877] to Lucy Hayes. This folder is located in Box 6 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - Montgomery, Josiah papers, 1862-1869
    Largely correspondence written by Montgomery to his mother. This folder is located in Box 6 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - Morrow, John W. papers, 1836-1894
    Collection consists of Morrow's business papers that cover a wide variety of legal and financial matters. Morrow appears to have specialized in the settlement and disposition of estates. Of note is the correspondence and legal materials of J.E. Hennigan of Texas. Morrow administered the estate of Hennigan's father and the papers reflect the facts of the estate but also family squabbles. The 1888 Articles of Incorporation for the Pineville Cotton mill, as well as two diaries, and an account book are also included.
  - Murdoch, Susan Butterworth papers, 1894-1912 and undated
    Diary, 1894-1900 (ca. 320 p.), kept by Susan B. Murdoch, and four miscellaneous items. The diary, written primarily from Maineville, Ohio, describes daily routines of a homemaker and wife as well as family concerns. There are additional entries for Benjamin Butterworth (1837-1898); the 2d Ohio Volunteer Infantry Regiment; floods; elections and women voting; and medical home remedies. An undated essay by Murdoch's husband describes pioneer life in Ohio.
  - Nadenbousch, John Quincy Adams papers, 1861-1871
    Included in this collection are Civil War papers relating to Nadenbousch's service as Provost-Marshall of Martinsburg, [West] Virginia and as a Captain in the "Stonewall" Brigade. Although several items of family correspondence appear, most letters concern military affairs.
  - New York, Miscellany papers, 1765-1924
    Miscellaneous items related to New York, largely correspondence. This folder is located in Box 6 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - North Carolina, Miscellany papers, 1806-1878
    This collection contains miscellaneous items related to North Carolina. Largely correspondence, included is a speech on women, written by North Carolina's first governor, Richard Caswell. This folder is located in Box 6 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - Norton, Mary papers, 1852-1895
    Chiefly letters from Clara Barton, founder and president of the American Red Cross, to Norton who was an intimate friend. Letters contain references to mutual friends and family and document the administration and operation of the Red Cross. Letters written during the Civil War include instructions for sending relief supplies and detailed observations which illustrate Barton's life in the trenches with the soldiers. Later letters concern Barton's travels, speaking engagements, and charity work; her life in Dansville, N.Y., as she contemplated the future of the Red Cross; and her work as the superintendent of the Reformatory Prison for Women in Southfarmington, Mass. A letter from Barton to her cousin Jerry details her breakdown in London, her views on the Stanley and Livingston affair, and her activities in France during the Franco-Prussian War. Other items include pamphlets on women's schools and charity organizations and a letter to Norton from P.T. Barnum discussing Horace Greeley.
  - Otis, Harrison Gray papers, 1803
    Letter is written to Otis from Alexander Hamilton, and discusses a civil suit related to trade between a New Jersey company and Para, Brazil. Hamilton mentions evidence from Portugal.
- P-R
  - Paca, William papers, 1782-1783
    Collection consists of four letters addressed to Paca. Most are requests from various persons, e.g., a British prisoner asking for his freedom and permission to settle in Annapolis with his family, a Maryland Representative writing on behalf of a woman seeking restitution for personal losses to the British, and a Baltimore man seeking an official pass to visit New York City on business. Another letter inventories the losses in the 1783 fire at the Annapolis armory.
  - Palliser, Hugh papers, 1770s[?]
    A note on the cover of a missing letter. The note refers to the enclosed letter on the 14th from Palliser, who has given intelligence information to the British regarding a vessel that is to be purchased or detained for His Majesty's use.
  - Payne, John Howard papers, undated
    Facsimile of Payne's "Home, Sweet Home." Located in Box 7 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - Pennsylvania, Miscellany papers, 1796-1915
    Miscellaneous correspondence written in Pennsylvania. Items are located in Box 7 of the Harry L. and Mary K. Dalton Collection.
  - Perry, Oliver Hazard papers, 1808-1813
    Three letters, two engravings of Perry, and an announcement of a public dinner given by the citizens of Washington, D.C. in honor of Perry's victory on Lake Erie in 1813. The letters, two of which are facsimiles, are written by Perry to Robert Smith, Secretary of the Navy, and General William Henry Harrison, and chiefly concern his military victory on Lake Erie, the delivery of prisoners following that event, and a recommendation that a William Prant Smith be given a midshipman's warrant.
  - Phillips, John papers, 1743-1798